Title: The bone collectors
Author: Daniel Di Falco<annotation class="PERSON">
Abstract: From where do all the bones come, and, importantly, should they be returned?

Skulls like these from the Basel Natural History Museum<annotation class="ORG"> were intended to preserve our memory of indigenous populations and protect their heritage from colonisation.
That’s how collectors saw it 100 years ago<annotation class="DATE">.
Today<annotation class="DATE">, descendants are demanding the return of their remains.
| Image: Valérie Chételat<annotation class="PERSON">
In the files, he’s called a ‘collector’.
However, he only carried his portable cooking utensils around with him, and that’s hardly the professional equipment of a man whose task is to skeletonise human corpses.
Nevertheless, it’s thanks to his efforts that the Basel Society for the Natural Sciences<annotation class="ORG"> was given “by far the most valuable addition” to its ethnological collection in the year 1914<annotation class="DATE">, as it wrote in its report for that year<annotation class="DATE">: “Two<annotation class="CARDINAL"> complete skeletons, one<annotation class="CARDINAL"> male and a young female, both Alacalufe<annotation class="NORP"> from Tierra del Fuego<annotation class="LOC">: specifically, the west coast of the island of Santa Inéz<annotation class="GPE">”.
This island lies at the southern point of South America<annotation class="LOC"> and today<annotation class="DATE"> belongs to Chile<annotation class="GPE">.
Our otherwise anonymous travelling ‘collector’ is said to have observed a funeral there, after which he promptly exhumed the bodies and then “boiled them down piece by piece in his travelling pan”, thus the annual report in Basel<annotation class="GPE">.
What remained were bones and skulls.
These lie today<annotation class="DATE"> in the anthropological collection of the Basel Natural History Museum<annotation class="ORG">.
This is an exceptional case, as Pierre-Louis Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> has been able to determine.
Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> studied biological anthropology and is currently working as a research assistant at the Rietberg Museum<annotation class="ORG"> in Zurich<annotation class="GPE">.
He is writing his doctoral thesis, entitled ‘Collecting humanity’<annotation class="WORK_OF_ART">, at the Department of Cultural and Science Studies<annotation class="ORG"> at the University of Lucerne<annotation class="ORG">, and is investigating the history of early human remains both in the Basel<annotation class="GPE"> collection and in the French National Museum of Natural History<annotation class="ORG"> in Paris<annotation class="GPE">.
The controversy comes 100 years later<annotation class="DATE">
The period Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> is examining is 1905 to 1918<annotation class="DATE">, and the objects of his study are the scientific and historical context of anthropology, the institutions and people involved in forming these collections, and the origins of the objects in them.
What is extraordinary about the Santa Inéz<annotation class="PERSON"> skeletons, he says, was not that the ‘collector’ dug them out of a grave; “exhumations were at the time a widespread method for acquiring human remains for anthropological study”.
Even Fritz<annotation class="PERSON"> and Paul Sarasin<annotation class="PERSON">, the founding fathers of the Basel<annotation class="GPE"> collection, procured bones from graves in Sri Lanka<annotation class="GPE"> and Sulawesi<annotation class="GPE">, in some cases without the knowledge of the indigenous inhabitants.
What was exceptional was the point in time when these bodies were exhumed, for digging up fresh corpses that had not yet decayed was “very rare”.
A hundred years later<annotation class="DATE">, an ethical unease has surfaced.
Human remains in museum collections have become a problematic matter, and demands for their restitution have resulted in controversy about the legacy of early anthropology.
In 2011<annotation class="DATE"> this climaxed in a foreign-policy crisis between Germany<annotation class="GPE"> and Namibia<annotation class="GPE">, when the presence of bones in German<annotation class="NORP"> collections raised direct questions about the genocide once perpetrated against the Herero<annotation class="NORP"> tribe in the former German<annotation class="NORP"> colony.
Pierre-Louis Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> explains that these concerns have been compounded by shifting sensibilities with regard to our relationship to death and the dead.
Back then, anthropological textbooks offered practical guidelines for exhuming bodies.
Even handling human flesh was “not problematic” at the time.
The Basel Society for the Natural Sciences<annotation class="ORG"> also had no compunction about making public the circumstances in which they acquired their two<annotation class="CARDINAL"> Fueguians<annotation class="ORG">, as they happily published the details in their annual<annotation class="DATE"> report.
And no one back then questioned whether those circumstances were either legal or legitimate.
Preserving endangered tribes
At the same time, the collectors didn’t just see themselves as beholden to science alone, explains Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON">, but also in a position of responsibility towards the indigenous peoples themselves.
The collectors believed them to be threatened by both modernity and colonisation, and they wanted to secure these peoples a place in human history by collecting cultural and biological evidence of their existence.
That is precisely why the bones of Santa Inéz<annotation class="PERSON"> were so “valuable” to the Basel Society<annotation class="ORG">; they were “the remains of a tribe that is dwindling without hope [of survival]”, as the Society<annotation class="ORG"> wrote.
Only parts of these two<annotation class="CARDINAL"> collections truly raise ethical concerns, Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> insists.
And where these exist, there is no guarantee that historical knowledge can help us find an answer to the questions we have today<annotation class="DATE">.
Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> hopes that his research will at least make a contribution to the “fundamental knowledge” that is often lacking in the debate – namely about the origins of the bones and just how they entered these collections in the first<annotation class="ORDINAL"> place.
“Many objects are badly documented”, he says, “and many museums have until now only engaged with the problems in a defensive manner”.
The Natural History Museum<annotation class="ORG"> of Basel<annotation class="GPE"> is supporting Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON">’s work.
The head of its anthropological collection Gerhard Hotz<annotation class="PERSON"> explains that it is part of a long-term programme in the field of provenance research.
In Paris<annotation class="GPE">, Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> experienced just how topical his historical work can be.
Since 1909<annotation class="DATE">, the French National Museum of Natural History<annotation class="ORG"> in Paris<annotation class="GPE"> has held the skull of a certain Mahmadou-Lamine<annotation class="NORP">, an indigenous leader in French<annotation class="NORP"> Sudan<annotation class="GPE"> and a victim of the colonial wars.
Through his work, Blanchard<annotation class="PERSON"> became aware of a petition from Mali<annotation class="GPE"> demanding the repatriation of the skull – and he was informed about it even before it had reached the museum authorities.
The case is still pending.
Daniel Di Falco<annotation class="PERSON"> is a historian and a journalist at the Bund<annotation class="ORG"> newspaper in Bern<annotation class="GPE">.
