<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Annotated_document>
  <Title>
    <text> Snapshots of research
</text>
  </Title>
  <Author>
    <text> Daniel Saraga<annotation class="PERSON"/>
</text>
  </Author>
  <Abstract>
    <text> The photos that Swiss<annotation class="NORP"/> researchers submitted to the SNSF Scientific Image Competition<annotation class="WORK_OF_ART"/> offer a surprising, nuanced picture of science.
They prompt astonishment, they inspire and they tell stories.
The image editor for Horizons<annotation class="ORG"/>, Valérie Chételat<annotation class="PERSON"/>, has chosen her own favourites from among them, independent of the jury’s decision.
</text>
  </Abstract>
  <Main_text>
    <text>Scientist at Work - Category "Men and women of science" | Jürg Sigrist<annotation class="PERSON"/>, biomedical scientist, EAWAG
SNSF Scientific Image Competition
They illustrate what researchers experience in their work, and show who they are: these are the images, photos and videos that were submitted for the new SNSF<annotation class="ORG"/> competition for scientific images.
Some 239<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> people from all regions of Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"/> took part.
In total, 437<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> images and 60<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> videos were submitted in the four<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> categories ‘Object of study’<annotation class="WORK_OF_ART"/>, ‘Men and women of science’, ‘Locations and instruments’ and ‘ Video loop’.
“The images submitted illustrate the fascinating diversity of scientific research”, says Pascal Hufschmid<annotation class="PERSON"/> of the Musée de l’Elysée<annotation class="ORG"/> in Lausanne<annotation class="GPE"/>, who was the president of the international jury that selected one<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> winner from each of the four<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> categories.
There were no microscopy images among the winners.
“This may come as a surprise”, says Matthias Egger<annotation class="PERSON"/>, the President of the National Research Council of the SNSF<annotation class="ORG"/>.
“In fact, it highlights the visual richness and the scope of scientific practice today<annotation class="DATE"/>”.
The jury’s selection and links to the images submitted can be found at www.snsf.ch/winning-images-2017
</text>
  </Main_text>
</Annotated_document>
