<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Annotated_document>
  <Title>
    <text> Horror films make faces look afraid
</text>
  </Title>
  <Author>
    <text> Jochen Paulus<annotation class="PERSON"/>
</text>
  </Author>
  <Abstract>
    <text> Horror films and comedies influence the faces we see.
</text>
  </Abstract>
  <Main_text>
    <text>Joy<annotation class="PERSON"/> or fear?
| Image: Emilie Qiao-Tasserit<annotation class="PERSON"/>
Alfred Hitchcock<annotation class="PERSON"/> once carried out a little experiment.
First<annotation class="ORDINAL"/> he showed a mother with her child in a meadow, then his own face with a neutral expression.
The audience saw Hitchcock<annotation class="PERSON"/> as a well-meaning old man.
Secondly<annotation class="ORDINAL"/>, he showed a dead child in its coffin, then the same photo of himself.
This time, the audience saw sadness in his face, explains cognitive scientist Swann Pichon<annotation class="PERSON"/> from the University of Geneva<annotation class="ORG"/>.
Emilie Qiao-Tasserit<annotation class="PERSON"/>, Pichon<annotation class="PERSON"/> and their colleagues have been investigating how filmic images alter our perception.
First<annotation class="ORDINAL"/> they showed their test subjects minute-long film excerpts from three<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> genres: the horror classic The Shining, the comedy When Harry met Sally<annotation class="WORK_OF_ART"/>, and a neutral documentary film about the mysteries of space.
Then they showed them photos of people with largely ambiguous facial expressions.
To this end, they morphed and varied two<annotation class="CARDINAL"/> photos of the same person, one with a fearful expression and the other happy.
Sometimes they made the face happier, at other times more fearful.
Their test subjects had to decide with each photo whether it showed a person who was happy or afraid.
Hitchcock<annotation class="PERSON"/> was right: the same photo looks happier to the audience when they’ve first<annotation class="ORDINAL"/> seen a clip from a comedy.
After seeing the horror clip, the same photo came across as more fearful.
The study also showed that the impact can last at least one-and-a-half minutes<annotation class="TIME"/>.
Now Pichon<annotation class="PERSON"/> is investigating how computer games influence the feelings and social behaviour of their players.
“Computer games often have a bad reputation – but our research shows that they can also have a positive impact”, says Pichon<annotation class="PERSON"/>.
</text>
  </Main_text>
</Annotated_document>
