Title: Clinical trials and tribulations
Author: Alexandra Bröhm<annotation class="PERSON">
Abstract: Some laboratory studies are being scuppered by overly optimistic researchers

Is Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"> missing the bus when it comes to international clinical research?
Without the proper personnel resources, you can’t carry out a well-organised intervention study.
Image: Keystone<annotation class="ORG">/Science Photo Library/Look at Sciences/Massimo<annotation class="PERSON">
Randomised controlled trials (‘RCT<annotation class="WORK_OF_ART"> studies’) are essential for medical progress.
But their cancellation rate is appallingly high.
For example, one<annotation class="CARDINAL"> out of four<annotation class="CARDINAL"> studies funded by the Swiss National Science Foundation SNSF<annotation class="ORG"> between 1986 and 2015<annotation class="DATE"> was cancelled early by its researchers.
This is the conclusion of a team led by the Basel<annotation class="GPE"> epidemiologist Matthias Briel<annotation class="PERSON">, whose results have now been published in the British Medical Journal<annotation class="ORG">.
It makes no difference whether the projects are funded by the SNSF<annotation class="ORG"> or not.
“It’s a fundamental problem”, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">, who is researching at the Basel University Hospital<annotation class="ORG">.
His team has analysed why so many RCTs end ahead of schedule.
The main problem, they find, lies in the early stages, namely in the recruitment of suitable participants.
“Often, the researchers’ estimates are too optimistic”, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">.
In other words, the doctors are confident there will be enough patients taking part without properly ensuring that the numbers are right.
In reality, not every patient will fulfil the inclusion criteria of a study, nor will everyone will be willing to participate either.
Especially where a lot of effort is involved.
Annette Magnin<annotation class="PERSON"> has experienced similar problems.
She’s the Managing Director of the Swiss Clinical Trial Organisation<annotation class="ORG"> (SCTO<annotation class="ORG">): “Researchers often overestimate their participant numbers by some 50 percent<annotation class="PERCENT"> before their studies even begin”, she says.
The SCTO<annotation class="ORG"> was founded on the initiative of the SNSF<annotation class="ORG"> and the Swiss Academy of Medical Sciences<annotation class="ORG"> (SAMS<annotation class="ORG">) in order to support doctors in clinical research.
Federalism limits the patient pool
“Another problem is that many studies are too regional in how they’re organised”, says Professor Peter Meier-Abt<annotation class="PERSON">, the Vice President of the SAMS<annotation class="ORG">.
Many hospitals in Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"> are too small to be able to rely on a satisfactory pool of patients.
The health system is organised on a federal basis, and most experts see this as a core issue in the optimal organisation of a clinical study.
“We really need an overall pool of patients”, says Meier-Abt<annotation class="PERSON">.
But coordinating such a pool across all of Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"> is difficult.
Briel<annotation class="PERSON"> also believes that “you don’t have to limit things regionally to a single Swiss<annotation class="NORP"> hospital”.
Studies that are run in several places can function very well if they are properly prepared and coordinated.
The experts are also of one<annotation class="CARDINAL"> mind with regard to another object of criticism: that doctors in Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"> are much too involved in everyday clinical work.
“We need more time to be allocated specifically for research”, says Meier-Abt<annotation class="PERSON">.
Doctors who are already putting in overtime can’t carry out research on their free evenings or at weekends.
Magnin<annotation class="PERSON"> also says: “Treating people is what actually brings in money for the hospitals; but as time goes by, it gets more and more difficult for their clinical personnel to invest time in research too”.
“We have to be careful that we don’t miss the boat, internationally speaking”, says Meier-Abt<annotation class="PERSON">.
Denmark<annotation class="GPE">, Sweden<annotation class="GPE"> and the Netherlands<annotation class="GPE"> are far more advanced than Switzerland<annotation class="GPE"> when it comes to research infrastructure.
And in the Anglo-Saxon<annotation class="NORP"> world, scholarly work carries far more weight.
The first<annotation class="ORDINAL"> initiatives are up and running
Initial attempts are being made to combat this problem.
Two years ago<annotation class="DATE">, the SNSF<annotation class="ORG"> initiated the programme ‘Investigator Initiated Clinical Trials<annotation class="PRODUCT">’ (IICT), with which it hopes to promote independent clinical research in Switzerland<annotation class="GPE">.
There is a budget of CHF 10 million<annotation class="MONEY"> available in 2017<annotation class="DATE">.
“We have extended the duration of RCTs from three to four years<annotation class="DATE">”, says Ayşim Yılmaz<annotation class="PERSON">, the head of the Biology and Medicine Division<annotation class="ORG"> of the SNSF<annotation class="ORG">.
This is intended to make it easier for researchers to carry out a proper preparatory phase.
“We also want to invest in innovative research”, says Yilmaz<annotation class="PERSON">.
There are no guarantees that a trial will succeed, but failure shouldn’t be used to excuse poor planning”.
Preparing something well is the best path to success, says Matthias Briel<annotation class="PERSON">, who is himself the author of a clinical study: “It’s best to carry out a controlled pilot study with the same study protocol”, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">.
Doctors aren’t always enthusiastic when they hear this, but various international investigations have confirmed it as a recipe for success.
What is also decisive, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">, is describing the recruiting process in detail in the study protocol.
“The researcher should also run through the ‘what-if’ scenarios at the preliminary stage”, he says.
“That way, you can minimise the damage, should your search for participating patients be proceeding sluggishly”.
Briel<annotation class="ORG"> sees social media platforms as a means of expanding the potential group of participants.
Initial trials have shown that social media can help to stimulate interest in a study.
Overall, the general public has to be sensitised to the fact that clinical research is for the good of everyone, but that it’s only possible if a lot of people are prepared to participate in studies.
The ethics commissions could also do their part in making the recruitment process as successful as possible.
“When assessing studies, they ought to make the researchers already aware of possible shortcomings in recruiting participants”, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">.
In the past, he adds, doctors have repeatedly complained that the administrative burden caused by such studies is a major hurdle.
Meanwhile, the procedure has been somewhat simplified.
Research has to be learned
The experts are also united in their belief that more should be invested in training young researchers: “Planning and carrying out clinical studies correctly is a discipline all of its own – one you have to learn”, says Magnin<annotation class="PERSON">.
Clinical Trial Units<annotation class="ORG"> exist today<annotation class="DATE"> at six<annotation class="CARDINAL"> Swiss<annotation class="NORP"> hospitals and act as service providers to the researchers.
But their support is costly.
Last year<annotation class="DATE">, the Federal Office of Public Health<annotation class="ORG"> launched a roadmap for promoting young clinical researchers.
One<annotation class="CARDINAL"> part of this package entails the creation of a Swiss Clinical Research Education Centre<annotation class="ORG">.
“Here in Switzerland<annotation class="GPE">, we need a clear commitment to clinical research”, says Magnin<annotation class="PERSON">.
Briel<annotation class="PERSON"> is also insistent that “all the key stakeholders must participate in these efforts, and assume their responsibilities in this vital field”.
The question remains as to what should happen with the data that is left unused after unfinished studies.
“It should be made generally available to later studies, either for meta-analyses or as lessons learned”, says Briel<annotation class="PERSON">.
The National Institute for Health Research (NIHR)<annotation class="ORG"> in Britain<annotation class="GPE">, for example, solved the problem by insisting that all studies it supports be published.
If that condition isn’t fulfilled, they don’t get any money.
Alexandra Bröhm<annotation class="PERSON"> is a science journalist at the Tages-Anzeiger<annotation class="FAC"> and the Sonntagszeitung<annotation class="FAC">.
